we lived in an economy of financial growth and prosperity.
كنا نعيش تحت ظل اقتصاد النمو المالي و الإزدهار
This was called the Great Moderation,
وكانت تلك الفترة تسمى بالاعتدال العظيم
the misguided belief by most economists,
الاعتقاد المظلل من قبل معظم الاقتصاديين
policymakers and central banks
صانعي القرار و البنوك المركزية
that we have transformed into a new world
أننا قد تحولنا إلى عالم جديد
of never-ending growth and prosperity.
من النمو و الإزدهار غير المنتهين
This was seen by robust and steady GDP growth,
و شوهد ذلك من خلال نمو الناتج المحلي القوي و الثابت
by low and controlled inflation,
من خلال التضخم المنخفض و المسيطر عليه
by low unemployment,
من خلال معدلات البطالة المنخفضة
and controlled and low financial volatility.
و التقلبات المالية المنخفضة و المسيطرعليها
But the Great Recession in 2007 and 2008,
و لكن الركود الإقتصادي في 2007 و 2008
the great crash, broke this illusion.
الانهيار الكبير, حطم كل هذا الوهم
A few hundred billion dollars of losses in the financial sector
بضع مئات من مليار دولار من الخسائر في القطاع المالي
cascaded into five trillion dollars
اندفعت إلى خمسة ترليونات دولار
of losses in world GDP
من الخسائر في الناتج المحلي الاجمالي للعالم
and almost $30 trillion losses
وخسارة حوالي 30 ترليون دولار
in the global stock market.
في سوق الأسهم العالمي
So the understanding of this Great Recession
و بالتالي فإن فهم هذا الركود الإقتصادي
was that this was completely surprising,
أن هذا كان مفاجئأ تماماً
this came out of the blue,
كان غير متوقعاً
this was like the wrath of the gods.
كان مثل غضب الآلهه
There was no responsibility.
لم تكن هناك مسؤولية
So, as a reflection of this,
وكإنعكاس لهذا
we started the Financial Crisis Observatory.
بدأنا بمرصد للأزمة المالية
We had the goal to diagnose in real time
وكان لدينا هدف التشخيص في الوقت المناسب
financial bubbles
للفقاعات المالية
and identify in advance their critical time.
و التحديد المتقدم لأوقاتهم الحرجة
What is the underpinning, scientifically, of this financial observatory?
ماهو الأساس-علميا- لهذا المرصد المالي ؟
We developed a theory called "dragon-kings."
طورنا نظرية تسمى بـ"التنانين الملوك"
Dragon-kings represent extreme events
تمثل التنانين الملوك الأحدات المتطرفة
which are of a class of their own.
والتي هي من فئة خاصة بهم
They are special. They are outliers.
خاصة و متطرفة
They are generated by specific mechanisms
يتم إنشاؤها من قبل آليات محددة
that may make them predictable,
التي قد تجعل منهم قابلين للتنبؤ
perhaps controllable.
ربما ممكن السيطرة عليها
Consider the financial price time series,
بالنظر إلى سلسلة زمنية من السعر المالي
a given stock, your perfect stock,
أو السهم المعطى أو سهمك المفضل
or a global index.
أو مؤشر عالمي
You have these up-and-downs.
لديك هذه صعودا و هبوطا
A very good measure of the risk of this financial market
القياس الجيد جدا لخطر هذا السوق المالي
is the peaks-to-valleys that represent
هو القمم و الوديان التي تمثل
a worst case scenario
في اسوأ الحالات
when you bought at the top and sold at the bottom.
عندما تشتري في القمة وتبيع في الأسفل
You can look at the statistics, the frequency of the occurrence
بالنظر إلى الاحصائيات , تكرر حدث
of peak-to-valleys of different sizes,
القمم و الوديان بأحجام مختلفة
which is represented in this graph.
و التي تمثل بهذا الرسم البياني
Now, interestingly, 99 percent
الآن-من المثير للاهتمام- 99 في المئة
of the peak-to-valleys of different amplitudes
من القمم و الوديان بسعات مختلفة
can be represented by a universal power law
تستطيع أن تُمثل الانخفاظ العالمي للقوة
represented by this red line here.
المتمثل بالخط الأحمر هنا
More interestingly, there are outliers, there are exceptions
المثير أكثر للإهتمام-هناك قمم متطرفة-هناك استثنائات
which are above this red line,
والتي هي أعلى هذا الخط الأحمر
occur 100 times more frequently, at least,
تحدث 100 مرة أكثر في كثير من الأحيان، على الأقل
than the extrapolation would predict them to occur
من استقراء وتنبؤ لها بالحدوث
based on the calibration of the 99 percent remaining
استنادا إلى معايرة ال 99 في المئة المتبقية
peak-to-valleys.
من القمم و الوديان
They are due to trenchant dependancies
وذلك وفقاً إلى تبعيات بارتر
such that a loss is followed by a loss
خسارة تتبعها خسارة
which is followed by a loss which is followed by a loss.
و التي تتبعها خسارة ة التي تتبعها خسارة
These kinds of dependencies
وهذه الأنواع من التبعيات
are largely missed by standard risk management tools,
غائبة إلى حد كبير من أدوات إدارة المخاطر القياسية،
which ignore them and see lizards
التي تتجاهلهم وترى السحالي
when they should see dragon-kings.
عندها سيرون التنانين الملوك
The root mechanism of a dragon-king
آلية جذر التنانين الملوك
is a slow maturation towards instability,
هو النضج البطيء نحو عدم الاستقرار
which is the bubble,
والتي هو الفقاعة
and the climax of the bubble is often the crash.
والمناخ في الفقاعة أحيانا يدمر
This is similar to the slow heating of water
هذا يشابة التسخين البطئ للماء
in this test tube reaching the boiling point,
في هذا الانبوب للوصول الي نقطة الغليان
where the instability of the water occurs
حيث يحدث عدم استقرار للماء
and you have the phase transition to vapor.
وعندك هنا مرحلة التحول الي بخار
And this process, which is absolutely non-linear --
وهذه العملية، التي هي تماما غير خطية
cannot be predicted by standard techniques --
لا يمكن التنبؤ بها من خلال تقنيات القياسية
is the reflection of a collective emergent behavior
هو انعكاس للسلوك الجماعي الناشئ
which is fundamentally endogenous.
والذي ينمو باطنيا بشكل أساسي
So the cause of the crash, the cause of the crisis
وبالتالي فإن سبب السقوط ، وسبب الأزمة
has to be found in an inner instability of the system,
والتي يمكن العثور عليه في عدم الاستقرار الداخلي للنظام
and any tiny perturbation will make this instability occur.
وأي اضطراب صغير سيجعل عدم الاستقرار يحدث
Now, some of you may have come to the mind
الآن، بعضكم قد يخطر علي بالهم
that is this not related to the black swan concept
أن هذا لا علاقة له مفهوم البجعة السوداء
you have heard about frequently?
هل سمعتم عنها مراراًا؟
Remember, black swan is this rare bird
تذكر، البجعة السوداء هو هذا الطائر النادر
that you see once and suddenly shattered your belief
الذي تراه مرة واحدة وفجأة سيحطم معتقدك
that all swans should be white,
أن جميع البجع يجب أن يكونوا بيض
so it has captured the idea of unpredictability,
لذلك فقد استولت عليها فكرة عدم القدرة على التنبؤ
unknowability, that the extreme events
قدرة غير معروفة , أن الأحداث المناخية المتطرفة
are fundamentally unknowable.
هي في الأساس مجهول
Nothing can be further
لا شيء يمكن أن يكون أبعد
from the dragon-king concept I propose,
من مفهوم التنين الملك الذي أقترحته
which is exactly the opposite, that most extreme events
وهو بالضبط عكس ذلك، أن الأحداث الأكثر تطرفا
are actually knowable and predictable.
هي في الواقع يمكن معرفتها ويمكن التنبؤ بها
So we can be empowered and take responsibility
حتى نتمكن من تمكين وتحمل المسؤولية
and make predictions about them.
ونضع تنبؤات عنهم
So let's have my dragon-king burn this black swan concept.
لذا لندع مفهومي الملك التنين يحرق مفهوم البجعة السوداء هذا.
(Laughter)
[ضحك]
There are many early warning signals
هناك العديد من إشارات الإنذار المبكر
that are predicted by this theory.
التي تنبأت بها هذه النظرية
Let me just focus on one of them:
اسمحوا لي بالتركيز على واحد منهم فقط
the super-exponential growth with positive feedback.
النمو فائقة التسارع مع ردود الفعل الإيجابية
What does it mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك؟
Imagine you have an investment
تخيل أن يكون لديك إستثمار
that returns the first year five percent,
العوائد في السنة الأولى خمسة في المئة
the second year 10 percent, the third year 20 percent,
السنة الثانية 10 في المئة، السنة الثالثة 20 في المئة
the next year 40 percent. Is that not marvelous?
العام المقبل 40 في المئة. هذا ليس بعجيب؟
This is a super-exponential growth.
هذا هو نمو فائقة التسارع
A standard exponential growth corresponds
يتوافق نمو التسارع القياسي
to a constant growth rate, let's say, of 10 percent
إلى معدل نمو مستمر، دعنا نقول، من 10 في المئة
The point is that, many times during bubbles,
وهذه النقطة هي أن، عدة مرات خلال الفقاعات
there are positive feedbacks which can be of many times,
هناك اصداء إيجابية والتي يمكن أن تكون من عدة مرات
such that previous growths enhance,
مثل أن معدلات النمو السابقة وتعزيز
push forward, increase the next growth
الدفع إلى الأمام، وزيادة النمو التالي
through this kind of super-exponential growth,
من خلال هذا النوع من النمو فائقة التسارع
which is very trenchant, not sustainable.
وهو باتر جدا، وليس مستديم
And the key idea is that the mathematical solution
والفكرة الأساسية هي أن الحل الرياضي
of this class of models exhibit finite-time singularities,
من هذه الفئة من النماذج يحمل شخصياته محدود في الوقت
which means that there is a critical time
وهو ما يعني أن هناك وقت حرج
where the system will break, will change regime.
حيث سينهار النظام ,سيتغير النظام
It may be a crash. It may be just a plateau, something else.
قد يكون حادث. قد يكون مجرد عائق، شيء آخر
And the key idea is that the critical time,
والفكرة الأساسية هي أن الوقت الحرج
the information about the critical time is contained
فالمعلومات حول الوقت الحرج أِحتُويت
in the early development of this super-exponential growth.
في التطوير المبكر من هذا النمو فائق التسارع
We have applied this theory early on, that was our first success,
لقد طبقنا هذه النظرية في وقت مبكر، كان ذلك أول نجاح لدينا
to the diagnostic of the rupture of key elements
إلى التشخيص من تمزق من العناصر الرئيسية
on the iron rocket.
على الصاروخ الحديدي
Using acoustic emission, you know, this little noise
باستخدام الانبعاثات الصوتية، كما تعلمون، وهذا القليل من الضوضاء
that you hear a structure emit, sing to you
أن تسمع هيكل تنبعث منها، تغني لك
when they are stressed, and reveal the damage going on,
عندما يتم التشديد عليها، وتكشف عن ضرر يحدث
there's a collective phenomenon of positive feedback,
هناك ظاهرة جماعية من ردود الفعل الإيجابية
the more damage gives the more damage,
والمزيد من الضرر يعطي المزيد من الضرر
so you can actually predict,
حتى تتمكن فعلا من التنبؤ
within, of course, a probability band,
في غضون ذلك، بالطبع احتمال الفرقة،
when the rupture will occur.
متى سيحدث تمزق
So this is now so successful that it is used
لذلك هذا هو الآن ناجحة بحيث يتم استخدامه
in the initial phase of [unclear] the flight.
التي يتم استخدامها في المرحلة الأولية لضبط الرحلة
Perhaps more surprisingly, the same type of theory
ربما الأكثر إثارة للدهشة، نفس النوع من نظرية
applies to biology and medicine,
ينطبق على علم الأحياء والطب
parturition, the act of giving birth, epileptic seizures.
الولادة، فعل الولادة، نوبات الصرع.
From seven months of pregnancy, a mother
من الشهر السابع من الحمل ’ الأم
starts to feel episodic precursory contractions of the uterus
تبدأ تشعر بتقلصات تمهيديه عرضية من الرحم
that are the sign of these maturations
التي هي علامة علي عملية التنمو
toward the instability, giving birth to the baby,
نحو عدم الاستقرار، ولادة الطفل
the dragon-king.
التنين الملك
So if you measure the precursor signal,
لذلك إذا كنت تقيس إشارة الانذار
you can actually identify pre- and post-maturity problems
يمكنك في الواقع تعريف المشاكل ما قبل وما بعد النضج
in advance.
مقدماً
Epileptic seizures also come in a large variety of size,
تأتي نوبات الصرع أيضا في مجموعة كبيرة ومتنوعة الاحجام
and when the brain goes to a super-critical state,
وعندما يذهب الدماغ إلى حالة حرجة متقدمة
you have dragon-kings which have a degree of predictability
لديك التنانين الملوك الذي لديها درجة من القدرة على التنبؤ
and this can help the patient to deal with this illness.
وهذا يمكن أن يساعد المريض في التعامل مع هذا المرض
We have applied this theory to many systems,
لقد طبقنا هذه النظرية على العديد من الأنظمة
landslides, glacier collapse,
الانهيارات الأرضية وانهيار الجبل الجليدي
even to the dynamics of prediction of success:
حتى مع ديناميكية التنبؤ بالنجاح
blockbusters, YouTube videos, movies, and so on.
الأفلام الرائجة ومقاطع الفيديو يوتيوب، والأفلام، وهلم جرا.
But perhaps the most important application
ولكن ربما كان التطبيق الأكثر أهمية
is for finance, and this theory
هو للتمويل، وهذه النظرية
illuminates, I believe, the deep reason
تنير، وأعتقد أن السبب العميق
for the financial crisis that we have gone through.
عن الأزمة المالية التي مررنا
This is rooted in 30 years of history of bubbles,
وتكمن جذور هذا في 30 سنة من التاريخ من الفقاعات
starting in 1980, with the global bubble
ابتداء من عام 1980، مع فقاعة العالمية
crashing in 1987,
تحطمها في عام 1987
followed by many other bubbles.
تليها فقاعات كثيرة أخرى
The biggest one was the "new economy" Internet bubble
كان أكبر واحد في "الاقتصاد الجديد" فقاعة الإنترنت
in 2000, crashing in 2000,
في عام 2000، تحطمها في عام 2000،
the real estate bubbles in many countries,
الفقاعات العقارية في العديد من البلدان
financial derivative bubbles everywhere,
الفقاعات المالية المشتقة في كل مكان
stock market bubbles also everywhere,
سوق الأوراق المالية فقاعات أيضا في كل مكان
commodity and all bubbles, debt and credit bubbles --
فقاعات السلع الأساسية وجميع الفقاعات والديون والائتمان
bubbles, bubbles, bubbles.
فقاعات، فقاعات، فقاعات
We had a global bubble.
لدينا فقاعة العالمية
This is a measure of global overvaluation
هذا هو مقياس المغالاة العالمية
of all markets, expressing what I call
من جميع الأسواق، معربا عن ما أسميه
an illusion of a perpetual money machine
وهم من آلة المال دائم
that suddenly broke in 2007.
التي أنهارت فجأة في عام 2007
The problem is that we see the same process,
والمشكلة هي أن نرى نفس العملية
in particular through quantitative easing,
ولا سيما من خلال التخفيف الكمي
of a thinking of a perpetual money machine nowadays
من التفكير في آلة المال دائم في الوقت الحاضر
to tackle the crisis since 2008 in the U.S., in Europe,
لمعالجة الأزمة منذ عام 2008 في الولايات المتحدة، في أوروبا
in Japan.
في اليابان
This has very important implications
وهذا له انعكاسات هامة جدا
to understand the failure of quantitative easing
لفهم الفشل من التسهيل الكمي
as well as austerity measures
فضلا عن تدابير التقشف
as long as we don't attack the core,
طالما أننا لا تهاجم الجوهر
the structural cause of this perpetual money machine thinking.
السبب الهيكلي من آلة المال دائم , التفكير
Now, these are big claims.
الآن، تلك مطالبات كبيرة
Why would you believe me?
لماذا كنت تصدقني؟
Well, perhaps because, in the last 15 years
حسنا، ربما لأنه، في السنوات ال 15 الماضية
we have come out of our ivory tower,
نخرج من برج عاجي لدينا
and started to publish ex ante --
وبدأ في النشر قبل وقوعها
and I stress the term ex ante, it means "in advance" —
وأشدد على مصطلح قبل وقوعها، وهو ما يعني "مقدما"
before the crash confirmed
قبل تأكيد تحطم
the existence of the bubble or the financial excesses.
وجود فقاعة أو تجاوزات مالية
These are a few of the major bubbles
هذه هي بعض من الفقاعات الرئيسية
that we have lived through in recent history.
التي عشناها خلال في التاريخ الحديث
Again, many interesting stories for each of them.
مرة أخرى، العديد من القصص المثيرة للاهتمام لكل منها
Let me tell you just one or two stories
اسمحوا لي ان اقول لكم قصص واحد أو اثنين فقط
that deal with massive bubbles.
التي تتعامل مع فقاعات ضخمة
We all know the Chinese miracle.
ونحن جميعا نعرف المعجزة الصينية
This is the expression of the stock market
هذا هو تعبير عن سوق الأوراق المالية
of a massive bubble, a factor of three,
من فقاعة ضخمة، وهو عامل من ثلاثة
300 percent in just a few years.
300 في المئة في غضون سنوات قليلة
In September 2007,
في سبتمبر 2007،
I was invited as a keynote speaker of a macro hedge fund
دعيت كمتحدث رئيسي صندوق التحوط الكلي
management conference,
إدارة المؤتمرات
and I showed to the conference a prediction
عرضت علي المؤتمر تنبؤ
that by the end of 2007, this bubble
أنه بحلول نهاية عام 2007، هذه الفقاعة
would change regime.
سيغير النظام
There might be a crash. Certainly not sustainable.
قد يكون هناك تحطم . بالتأكيد ليست مستدامة
Now, how do you believe the very smart,
الآن، كيف كنت تعتقد أن الذكاء العالي
very motivated, very informed macro hedge fund managers
متحفزين، مطلعين جيدا مديرو صندوق التحوط الكلي
reacted to this prediction?
ورد على هذا التوقع؟
You know, they had made billions
تعلمون، أنها قدمت المليارات
just surfing this bubble until now.
مجرد تصفح هذه الفقاعة حتى الآن
They told me, "Didier,
قالوا لي: "ديدييه"
yeah, the market might be overvalued,
نعم، قد يكون المبالغة في تقدير قيمة السوق
but you forget something.
ولكنك نسيت شيئا
There is the Beijing Olympic Games coming
هناك ألعاب بكين الاوليمبية القادمة
in August 2008, and it's very clear that
في أغسطس 2008، وأنه من الواضح جدا أن
the Chinese government is controlling the economy
الحكومة الصينية تسيطرة على الاقتصاد
and doing what it takes
وتقوم بما يتطلبه الأمر
to also avoid any wave and control the stock market."
لتجنب أيضا أي موجة ومراقبة سوق الأوراق المالية
Three weeks after my presentation,
بعد ثلاثة أسابيع من العرض الذي قدمته
the markets lost 20 percent
خسرت الأسواق 20 في المئة
and went through a phase of volatility,
ومرت مرحلة من التقلبات
upheaval, and a total market loss of
الاضطراب، وفقدان السوق الكلي
70 percent until the end of the year.
لـ 70 في المئة حتى نهاية العام
So how can we be so collectively wrong
فكيف يمكننا أن نُكون مخطئين جماعيا
by misreading or ignoring the science
بواسطة قراءة خاطئة أو تجاهل العلم
of the fact that when an instability has developed,
من حقيقة أنه عندما وضعت حالة من عدم الاستقرار
and the system is ripe, any perturbation
والنظام مهيأة لأي اضطراب
makes it essentially impossible to control?
يجعل من المستحيل أساسا سيطرته ؟
The Chinese market collapsed, but it rebounded.
انهار السوق الصيني ، لكنه انتعشت
In 2009, we also identified that this new bubble,
في عام 2009، ونحن أيضا تحديد أن هذه الفقاعة الجديدة
a smaller one, was unsustainable,
أصغر واحد،غير قابل للاستمرار
so we published again a prediction, in advance,
ولذا فإننا نشرنا مرة أخرى التنبؤ، مقدما
stating that by August 2009, the market will correct,
مشيرا إلى أنه بحلول أغسطس 2009، السوق سوف يعتدل
will not continue on this track.
لن يستمر على هذا المسار.
Our critics, reading the prediction,
نقادنا قرأوا التنبأت
said, "No, it's not possible.
وقالوا: "لا، انها ليست ممكنة"
The Chinese government is there.
"الحكومة الصينية هناك"
They have learned their lesson. They will control.
"لقد تعلموا الدرس. فإنهم سيسيطرون عليها"
They want to benefit from the growth."
"انهم يريدون الاستفادة من النمو "
Perhaps these critics have not learned their lesson previously.
ربما هؤلاء النقاد لم يتعلموا الدرس من قبل
So the crisis did occur. The market corrected.
لذلك لم تحدث الأزمة.إعتدل السوق
The same critics then said, "Ah, yes,
ثم قال نفس النقاد، "آه، نعم"
but you published your prediction.
ولكن قمت بنشر تنبؤ الخاص بك
You influenced the market.
لقد أثرت علي السوق
It was not a prediction."
لم يكن هذا تنبؤاً
Maybe I am very powerful then.
ربما أنا قوي جدا حينها
Now, this is interesting.
الآن، هذا مثير للاهتمام
It shows that it's essentially impossible until now
لكنه يظهر أنه من المستحيل أساسا حتى الآن
to develop a science of economics
لتطوير علم الاقتصاد
because we are sentient beings who anticipate
لأننا الكائنات الحية الذين يتوقعون
and there is a problem of self-fulfilling prophesies.
وهناك مشكلة تحققيق التنبؤ ذاتياً
So we invented a new way of doing science.
لذلك نحن اخترعنا طريقة جديدة لممارسة العلم
We created the Financial Bubble Experiment.
أنشأنا تجربة الفقاعة المالية
The idea is the following. We monitor the markets.
الفكرة هي التالية. نحن نراقب الأسواق
We identify excesses, bubbles.
نحدد التجاوزات، الفقاعات
We do our work. We write a report
نحن نقوم بعملنا. نكتب تقرير
in which we put our prediction of the critical time.
الذي وضعنا به توقعاتنا للوقت حرج
We don't release the report. It's kept secret.
نحن لاننشر التقرير. تبقى عل سريتها
But with modern encrypting techniques,
ولكن مع تقنيات التشفير الحديثة
we have a hash, we publish a public key,
لدينا تجزئة، نقوم بنشر المفتاح العام
and six months later, we release the report,
وبعد ستة أشهر، نقوم بنشر التقرير
and there is authentication.
وهناك مصادقية.
And all this is done on an international archive
ويتم كل هذا على الأرشيف الدولي
so that we cannot be accused of just releasing the successes.
بحيث أننا لا نستطيع أن نتهم فقط بنشر النجاحات
Let me tease you with a very recent analysis.
اسمحوا لي مضايقتكم مع تحليل حديث جدا
17th of May, 2013, just two weeks ago,
17مايو 2013، قبل أسبوعين فقط
we identified that the U.S. stock market
حددنا أن سوق الأسهم في الولايات المتحدة
was on an unsustainable path
كان على مسار غير مستديم
and we released this on our website on the 21st of May
وأصدرنا هذا على موقعنا على 21 مايو
that there will be a change of regime.
أنه سيكون هناك تغيير النظام
The next day, the market started to change regime, course.
في اليوم التالي، بدأت السوق لتغيير النظام، وبطبيعة الحال
This is not a crash.
هذا ليس الحادث
This is just the third or fourth act
هذا هو مجرد الفعل الثالث أو الرابع
of a massive bubble in the making.
من فقاعة ضخمة في طور التكوين
Scaling up the discussion at the size of the planet,
توسيع نطاق المناقشة في حجم كوكب الأرض
we see the same thing.
ونحن نرى الشيء نفسه
Wherever we look, it's observable:
أينما نظرنا، انها يمكن ملاحظتها
in the biosphere, in the atmosphere, in the ocean,
في المحيط الحيوي، في الغلاف الجوي، في المحيط
showing these super-exponential trajectories
تظهر هذه المسارات فائقة التسارع
characterizing an unsustainable path
تميز مسار غير مستدام
and announcing a phase transition.
وأعلن عن مرحلة انتقالية
This diagram on the right
هذا الرسم البياني على اليمين
shows a very beautiful compilation of studies
يظهر تجميعا جميلة جدا من الدراسات
suggesting indeed that there is a nonlinear -- possibility
مما يوحي فعلا بأن هناك غير الخطية - إمكانية
for a nonlinear transition just in the next few decades.
للانتقال غير الخطية فقط في العقود القليلة القادمة
So there are bubbles everywhere.
لذلك هناك فقاعات في كل مكان
From one side, this is exciting
من جانب واحد، وهذا هو مثير
for me, as a professor who chases bubbles
بالنسبة لي، كأستاذ الذي يطارد الفقاعات
and slays dragons, as the media has sometimes called me.
ويذبح التنانين، بما أن وسائل الإعلام احيانا تطلقه علي
But can we really slay the dragons?
ولكن هل يمكننا حقا اذبح التنانين؟
Very recently, with collaborators,
مؤخرا جدا، مع المتعاونين
we studied a dynamical system
درسنا نظام ديناميكيا
where you see the dragon-king as these big loops
حيث ترى الموك التنانين بهذه الحلقات كبيرة
and we were able to apply tiny perturbations at the right times
وكنا قادرين على تطبيق اضطرابات صغيرة في الأوقات الصحيحة
that removed, when control is on, these dragons.
سيتم أزلتها عندما نتحكم بهؤلاء التنانين
"Gouverner, c'est prévoir."
"إن الحكم هو التنبؤ"
Governing is the art of planning and predicting.
الإدارة هي فن التخطيط والتنبؤ
But is it not the case that this is probably
ولكن تلك ليست الحاله هذا ربما
one of the biggest gaps of mankind,
واحدة من أكبر الفجوات البشرية
which has the responsibility to steer
الذي يتحمل المسؤولية لتوجيه
our societies and our planet toward sustainability
مجتمعاتنا وكوكبنا نحو الاستدامة
in the face of growing challenges and crises?
في مواجهة التحديات والأزمات المتزايدة؟
But the dragon-king theory gives hope.
ولكن نظرية التنانين الملوك يعطي الأمل
We learn that most systems have pockets of predictability.
ونحن نعلم ان معظم الأنظمة تحتوي على جيوب من القدرة على التنبؤ
It is possible to develop advance diagnostics of crises
فمن الممكن تطوير وسائل التشخيص قبل الأزمات
so that we can be prepared, we can take measures,
حتى نتمكن من أن نكون مستعدين، ونأخذ تدابيرنا
we can take responsibility,
يمكننا تحمل المسؤولية
and so that never again will
وذلك لن يكون ابدا مرة أخرى
extremes and crises like the Great Recession
النقيضين والأزمات مثل الكساد العظيم
or the European crisis take us by surprise.
أو الأزمة الأوروبية تأخذنا على حين غرة
Thank you.
شكرا
(Applause)
تصفيق